Guide to the I. Cyrus Gordon - Abraham Lincoln Collection
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
I. Cyrus Gordon - Abraham Lincoln Collection,
1846-1980.
Gordon, I. Cyrus, 1901-1980, collector.
ca. 350 items (7 boxes, l map case drawer & 7 unboxed items).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078433
Biographical Note
Israel Cyrus Gordon (Columbia A.B., 1924; LLB, 1926), a lawyer, was an avid collector of Lincolniana.
Scope and Content
Letters, documents, memorabilia, printed material, prints, medals and sculpture relating to Lincoln and the Civil War period. Included are a letter from Edward Everett, a Philip Henry Sheridan autograph, a document by W. H. Herndon, Linclon's law partner, 19th century leters and documents and 20th century clippings, pictures, etc. of or about Lincoln. The collection features a John Rogers sculpture, "The Council of War," several busts of Lincoln and other two and three dimensional works of art.
Arrangement
Selected items cataloged; remainder arranged by subject and genre.
Subjects
Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.--Portraits, caricatures, etc.; United States--History--Civil War, 1860-1865.; Photoprints; Sculpture; Prints
Acquisition
07/07/86 M-86-07-07 Papers and artwork Gordon, Donald J. and Ross, Susan Gordon Gift
Gift of Donald J. Gordon and Susan Gordon Ross, 1986.
- Series I: Cataloged correspondence
  - Everett, Edward (Box 1)
  - Sheridan, Philip Henry (Box 1)
- Series II: Cataloged Documents
  - Herndon, William Henry (Box 1)
- Series III: Cataloged Photograph
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 1)
- Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
  - 19c. (Box 1)
  - 19c. - Ackerman family (Box 1)
  - 19c. - Lincoln -facsimiles (Box 1)
  - 20c. - Sterrett, J.E. (Box 1)
  - 20c. - Correspondence about Gordon's collection (Box 1)
- Series V: Arranged Manuscripts
  - Gordon -Lists of Lincolnians (Box 1)
  - Gordon - Research on 14 March 1860 Lincoln letter to James Babcock (Box 1)
- Series VI: Arranged Documents
  - Civil War discharges (Box 1)
  - Civil War money (Box 1)
  - Gordon - Personal documents (Box 1)
  - Lincoln - Facsimile documents (Box 1)
  - Slave deed - Louisiana, 4 October 1859 (Box 1)
- Series VI: Memorabilia
  - Stamps -Lincoln & Civil War memorial (Box 1)
- Series VII: Printed Material
  - Ephemera:
    - 19c. (Box 1)
    - 19c. facsimile (Box 1)
    - 20c. (Box 1)
  - Lincoln:
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs (Box 1)
    - Misc. (Box 1)
    - Pictures (Box 1)
  - Lincolniana (Box 1)
  - Rogers, John, 1829-1904 (Box 1)
  - Gordon card files: (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Index (Box 2)
    - Topical Index (Box 2)
  - Documents: (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Ackerman family deeds and cemetery deeds (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Gordon -Personal documents (Box 3 (Flat Box))
  - Printed material:
    - Linen tea towel (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Misc. (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Reprints & facsimiles (Box 3 (Flat Box))
  - Prints:
    - Holcomh & Davis, "Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States", [1860] (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Lez, Felix, "Lincoln", n.d. (Box 3 (Flat Box))
    - Volk, Douglas, [Abraham Lincoln], c1922 (Box 3 (Flat Box))
- Oversized Materials
  - Cataloged: (Box 13-06-05)
    - Currier & Ives, "The Assassination of President Lincoln", New York, c1865 (Box 13-06-05)
    - -----. "The Deathbed of the Martyr President Abraham Lincoln". [New York], c1865 (Box 13-06-05)
    - -----, "Surrender of General Lee, At Appomattox Court House, Va., April 9th 1865". NY, c1865. (Box 13-06-05)
  - Uncataloged:
    - Kurz & Allison, "The Fort Pillow Massacre", Chicago, c1892 (Box 13-06-05)
- Artwork
  - Volk, Leonard Wells: (Box 4)
    - Casts of Lincoln's hands (Box 4)
    - Cast of Lincoln's death mask (Box 4)
  - Two reproductions of Lincoln Memorial statue (Box 5)
  - Metal images of Lincoln: (Box 6)
    - Round penny portrait (Box 6)
    - Oval plaque made for the Republican Club of the City of New York, 1910. (Box 6)
    - Reproduction of Springfield, Ill. memorial (Box 6)
    - Facsimile Lincoln medals (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous. Medals:
    - Bicentennial (1) (Box 6)
    - Civil War (2) (Box 6)
    - Sir Thomas Raffles (1) (Box 6)
  - Seven medals with Lincoln's profile, in a frame (Box 7 (Flat Box))
  - Three 20c. Silhouettes on celluloid (Box 7 (Flat Box))
  - Cataloged artwork:
    - Rogers. John "The Council of War". 1868
  - Arranged artwork:
    - Berks, Robert "Lincoln of the Gettysburg Address". sculpture of
    - Lincoln's head. Alvastone reproduction of bronze original at the Lincoln, Museum, Washington, D.C.
    - Lincoln's head in Alvastone reproduction
    - Lincoln bust in plaster
    - Plaque for Gordon's 70th birthday with 70 Lincoln head pennies
    - Plaque with Lincoln's profile
    - Plaque of Lincoln Memorial in bas-relief